Okay so now I want to talk about how you go about making your own wavetables in
Serum and firstly I wanted to talk about understanding how Serum works and the
actual harmonics involved. So before I started using Serum I used to use FM8
a lot which is a frequency modulation synthesizer and things work a little bit
differently in that aspect so instead of... where's Serum? Serum oscillators they
have obviously what we talked about the octave and the semitones and obviously
you can pitch that in relation to the musical scale. With frequency
modulation it works a little bit different. Instead of having octaves and
semitones it has frequencies based on the fundamental frequency you're
physically playing in your DAW. Now that might sound a little bit confusing
but it should make a little more sense. So the first thing I
wanted to do is talk about this section of Serum which is the table
So across here you can see lots of vertical bars and in Serum they're
called bins. So if I select bin 1 let me just quickly draw in a MIDI file
I'm gonna put that a little lower so we've got a kind of subby sound. Now I'm
gonna open up my frequency analyzer and as you can see I put the note on D
sharp and it's playing one single sine wave at D sharp. Now if I go back to my
editor if you click on this button here it will translate the actual
waveform to its harmonic so if you click here cool. Now if I press or if
I select bin 2 and I press play and look at my frequency analyzer again
I've got my existing sine wave at D sharp and then there's another harmonic
which is also D sharp. Now what happens if I go 3? Now if you're not familiar
with how harmonic distribution works in terms of Serum and frequency
modulation this may be a bit confusing so maybe a lot of people would
expect if I selected three it would be three semitones higher which would also
be a D sharp but it isn't so if I play this now so I've got my first one D
sharp I've got my second harmonic D sharp again and then my third one is
an A sharp. Now why is that? So instead of this working with semitones
and octaves this works in actual multiplication of your fundamental
frequency. So now I've set this to D sharp as you've just seen I'm gonna
take away my extra harmonics so what I like to use a lot when I first
started getting into synthesis I started using some like helpers so I've made a
really crude spreadsheet for myself which I'll quickly show you now. So this
is kind of my helper spreadsheet I've got lots of different little bits on
there which if I need them I can just open the spreadsheet and get the
information. So I've got my first harmonic selected which as we know is
a D sharp so if I go back to D sharp and the one I'm playing is this one so
on this on this little sheet here it says the note you're playing it says
the frequency range and the length of the waveform you can ignore the second
one for now it's not relevant for this particular subject. So we are
hitting at 77.7 Hertz to be correct which is if you look here which is
about right cool now if I press the second one it's a D sharp but it's a
hundred and fifty six Hertz so if I go to D sharp here and just show you
D sharp three I think yeah hundred and fifty five Hertz great so now if I
select three like I did before we have an A sharp which is
two hundred and thirty three now so why is it why is it doing that so if
I go back to my fundamental I'm gonna get out my calculator and show you
exactly why it's doing that and why behaves that way so if I take my
fundamental frequency I'm playing 77.78 Hertz now if I put this in my
calculator and times this by two I get a hundred and fifty five point five
six which is a D sharp again great now if I go here if I times this now by
three I get two hundred and thirty three which is an A sharp so what
this is physically doing in serum it's taking your fundamental frequency so
bin 1 and bin 2 bin 3 bin 4 bin 5 etc are timesing from your fundamental
frequency so for example bin 5 will be five times the frequency of your
fundamental so let's give that a test so if I go back to my fundamental
frequency which is 77.78 D sharp that's why I've selected in my door
times it by five I've got 388 which is which isn't right it's somewhere in
between there for some reason okay so 388 is G let's say it's G it's close
enough now if I select bin 5 and let's analyze this on a frequency spectrum
I've got a G right so that's the basics of how the table editor works
in serum and that's also the basics of how frequency modulation works in
terms of selecting the harmonic in your in your synthesizer so if any of
you have used FMA or I think there's citrus I think it's called in FL those
are good examples of frequency modulation right so how can you use
this in your music and what I wanted to show you was I quickly made a
baseline before this I'll quickly play this now so you can see it's very
harmonically rich loud and if we look in a spectrum analyzer you'll see here
frequency D sharp and I've got this massive peak around this area so let's
have a look okay so again that's hitting a G that's pretty pretty
similar to what we just did in serum now if I wanted to go and if I if
I wanted to go and literally recreate this sound for whatever purpose I could
go into serum I'm gonna select two oscillators I'll have one as my
fundamental so I have a bit more control over that obviously gonna turn
the randoms down and the only thing I'm gonna select on here is harmonic
5 which is bin 5 so let's have a little listen to what that sounds like okay I'm
gonna turn this down an octave so we have D sharp and I'm gonna turn this
down an octave as well
let's quickly analyze that again I think it was one octave higher let's
check
yeah so it's 300 around 300 Hertz cool so that can go one octave right so
obviously there's a lot of modulation going on in that sound so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna try and really roughly recreate that so the
first thing I can hear is there's a lot more harmonics it's a lot richer and
the reason for that is probably because of distortion so let's go to
my distortion and let's add this mega group mega distortion group so in
here I've got let's have a look I've got a chain with amplitude I've got a
chain with a wave shaper I'll quickly go through these a bit more in detail
in a second I have a guitar rig which we used earlier and I've just
got some trash on the end all right let's take a listen to how this sounds
right and let me put my just close this let me put this after the
distortion now so you can see it's a lot richer but we're adding lots of
lots of extra lots of extra harmonics in there and obviously the
distortion is creating that so let's add a little bit of modulation and see
where we get so what I'm gonna do is literally just put some volume
automation on this on my fundamental frequency so what's happening the only
thing I've done here is I'm turning down the actual sub when I say the sub
I mean the fundamental this note here and what's happening is because it's
being pushed so hard into into so much distortion like as I just showed
you there's two guitar amps there there's a wave shaper and there's an
isotope trash as well it's quite a lot because I'm pushing it so hard the
distortion is changing and compensating for that so if I turn
this down I get very harsh sound now we can utilize that effect so to speak now if I
put an LFO on this let's make a bit more interesting so the higher I go let
me just turn this around
there you go so that's a really really really simple way of understanding how
your harmonics work in serum and it's a really simple and effective way to
create a really cool baseline very quickly so let's see what happens if I
change harmonics so now we were on bin 5 so if I quickly go back to my
sheet being five so I could do the calculation here or you could not do
it at all it's completely up to you and it's completely it depends on how far
you want to take this I love doing this type of stuff because it really gives
me a mental vision of what I'm trying to achieve the more you understand the
more fun it is and easier is so instead of using a calculator to
calculate all these I've made a little very crude sheet here these are
my bins harmonics so if I select so if I've got D sharp and I've got bin 5 I
know that's a G so let's try bin 6 see what that sounds like and that'll
be in a sharp also sounds very cool let's try bin 7 also very cool and let's
try 8 and as you'll notice here 8 is again a D sharp because if you times
obviously because it's an odd number if you times it oh sorry even if you
times it with a fundamental you always get a D sharp so let's try that in
8 so you can hear it's like a D sharp on a D sharp but it feels like
it's peaching up which is very cool effect and secondly you can have a big
mix of them
which also sounds very cool and then we can obviously take this further and
develop the sound a bit more so we can add some unison there and now because
I'm adding unison with a detune it's very similar to what the effect we had
when we made the recess when we detune and we've actually phased them
out you can see it's almost giving a kind of LFO effect but very cool and
very interesting to listen to let's extend this a little bit longer take
that loop off I'm gonna turn this down a bit because a bit loud
that kind of works I could definitely use that in a tune so I'm gonna save
that great so I want to show you a couple more examples of how I like to
use wavetables so let's duplicate this serum and let's try and develop this
into something a bit more now so if I go to my or if I go to oscillate one
where I've put where I've put the harmonics in selected them myself now
what I can do is I can gradually automate the levels on this sound so I
can select frame 2 and then I can make some edits let's go with 3 something
like that and now when I change my wavetable position
I get some really interesting cool things going on there that's sounding
pretty cool now let's see what happens if I FM this so very loud kind of
bassy sound very over-the-top and I'm sure you can all imagine what type of
tune this would work in cool so developing that a bit more from there
something like that which is a little more interesting a little more
interesting in the tone as well and the reason why is because it's
changing this one's very static which could work in a tune but now I've got
another option which is great so this is a really cool way to make wavetables
in serum make your own wavetables and soon in a very simple way the next
thing I want to show you is how to make very creative wavetables in serum
by using samples so I'm going to take a quick break and then we'll get to
that in a second okay so another really cool option with serum because
it can because what I showed you before with harmonics in the wavetable serum
enables you to actually load any sample you want into any oscillator and what
it will do is will calculate those harmonics for you so you can get some
really interesting sounds by just using kind of random random samples
basically so I wanted to quickly give that a go on the fly and see if we
can create something cool so I just quickly went through my sample foley
library and I found this jet sound which is kind of cool sounding could
just use in a tune like that actually but what I wanted to do is you have
an option in serum so if I don't let me go back to where it was if I take this
jet sound and then if I drop it into if I drop it into an oscillator I have
all these three options now what I normally do is import normal dynamic
pit drain zero snap and then it will give a few minutes at cool so now this
jet sound has been loaded in so let me activate that I have a MIDI file being
triggered on that serum patch so if I play you can't hear anything and the
reason why you can't hear anything is because this is flat and set zero so we
need to do a bit of editing so if I open up my wavetable if I scroll along
a few frames here you can see all of a sudden start to get some sound so I
just need to clean this up a bit so I'm gonna select to about here go to
the start if you go to add and remove remove current index and it will take
you to start that didn't work very well let's do that again remove
multi-section that was the one so if you select remove multi-section what
they'll do is remove all the frames with nothing in them so as you can
see here now I've just got this kind of flimsy tone so what I can do now is
because serum has split that sound which I imported into lots of different
frames if I change the wavetable position it will go frame frame by
frame through that sound so if we put an LFO on here set this to something
slow like two bars what it's doing is it's literally flicking through that
wavetable so let's make this a bit shorter okay there's something cool
going on in this section so what I can do if I like that section I can just
go it's about halfway I think it's kind of cool it's very low I'm gonna put an
octave higher just gonna see if I can improve this see what happens if we
make it faster bit random cool so now what I'm gonna do is I'm going to back
this up with some standard wavetable so I'm gonna use a sine wave I'm gonna
put this an octave lower so some sub in there and what I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna try and match these two together and try and complete try
make a complete sound so the goal here is to create something which you
necessarily wouldn't be able to create in a synthesizer because we have such
a crazy and erratic set of harmonics going on here it gives us something
really unique so let's first automate the level of this something like
something with a bit more groove to it again let's turn these randoms down not
bad I am going to FM from a find a sweet spot too much cool that's got
something cool about it maybe I could put this an octave higher I'm gonna turn
this sub down a little bit let's add some distortion I've already got trash
up a bit better let's try and add some unison to this okay cool that's a lot
more interesting what I want to do is look at my frequency spectrum here to
see what's happening give it a bit of room cool so let's add some different
effects to it and see if we can improve this very phasey I'm not sure about
that that's a cool sound but it's very very again phasey I'm gonna try
and counteract that by adding another sub using the sub oscillator gonna use
exactly the same wavetable exactly the same automation but I'm gonna put this
direct out let's go an octave down I think I want to take some low end out
of this sound now with the filter section you can obviously select which
oscillator you want to filter so I'm only going to select a and I'm going
to use a high 12 let's isolate this I'm gonna put some automation on this
let's add a bit of drive to it obviously too much way too much drive cool that's
not bad with these type of sounds it's very reliant on what sounds you're
putting into serum and how serum deals with that a lot some sounds I'll put
in and they really won't work at all some sounds I'll drop in and
literally you'll have an instant base so if you guys have a spare hour to
be creative and try and make sounds like that give it a go because this
is a really fun way to to utilize serum and also you'll get a much better
understanding on how this how the wavetables work in serum it will set
you up so when you are working in your tunes later you have a much
stronger mental image of what the sounds physically doing cool so I've got
a nice selection of bass sounds and effects here and I've got a nice
selection of drums as well so I can almost start writing my tune what I want
to cover next is my approach to actually physically writing a tune and
what I do or what I like to do a lot is actually start with a melody I
really love melody in my tunes I mean we're musicians so let's write
music even if some of my tunes are really pushed and really distorted I
still love to have a musical element in there somewhere so what we're gonna do
is we are going to look at how scales and melodies work in music and then
apply that to writing an intro for our tune and then from the intro we're
gonna build the tune to whatever we feel will fit the intro and this is
fundamental for me because it's like right writing music so so yeah I'm
really excited and and I'll see you in the next one